Jesse M. Harrison Papers VHP2005/22
CCSU Veterans History Project
Jesse M. Harrison Papers
Bulk, 1942-1946
1942 - 1956, 2005
VHP2005/22
CCSU Veterans History Project
112.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
The collection details Jesse M. Harrison's experience as a pilot in the 77th Troop Carrier Squadron, US Air force during World War II which he flew Douglas C-47, a military transport aircraft, over Europe. Materials in the collection include an oral history interview, Jesse Harrison's published biography, and photographs.
Harrison, Jesse M., 1921 -
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Biographical/Historical note
Jesse M. Harrison volunteered for the U.S. Air Force in 1942. He passed the required tests and attended flight school at Randolph Field, in San Antonio, TX. He aspired to be a fighter pilot, and after his graduation from flight school in March of 1943, he received his commission as 2nd lieutenant and his assignment as a pilot in the 77th Troop Carrier Squadron. The Squadron flew overseas with a destination of Nottingham, England, however when they were due to land, a heavy fog prevented them from landing at the correct airport. The crew had mistakenly landed in Ireland at a military airfield. Because Ireland was a neutral territory they were taken into custody, and the men did not continue on to England until they escaped from the base in the middle of the night a week later. Due to the landing in a neutral country, the crew was then placed under house arrest by U.S. MP's for 30 days when they did make it to England. After the imprisonment, Harrison's crew returned to base, and flew paratroopers into the Invasion of Normandy. Of the squadron of 12 planes from his unit in the invasion, Harrison witnessed two planes of theirs get shot down by enemy fire. Although there was intense danger, Harrison completed his mission, for which he earned the Distinguished Flying Cross. In another act of bravery, Harrison was shot down in Holland while towing a glider. He would not abandon the plane because the glider with men on it was still attached. He waited until they could disengage themselves from the plane before parachuting out himself. When he did finally jump, it was only a few hundred feet from the ground. Harrison suffered intense burns on his hands, and although he was in and out of consciousness for weeks after the accident, he remembers that he was saved by two Dutch priests that were in the woods near where he had gone down. Harrison received the Purple Heart and the Silver Star for his actions in Holland
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Technical metadata of digital objects are extracted and encoded in PREMIS preservation metadata format
Preservation Metadata
United States. Air Force. Troop Carrier Squadron, 77th.; United States. Army Air Forces.; Distinguished Flying Cross (Medal); England; France; Holland (Netherlands: Province); Interviews; Ireland; Manuscript; Photographs; Randolph Field (Tex.); Sheppard Field (Tex.); World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- France -- Normandy; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations.
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2005/22.I
  - Jesse Harrison Biography (Book), 2005; VHP2005/22.I.1; 106.0 Digital objects
  - Interview synopsis, Dec. 2, 2005; VHP2005/22.I.2; 106.0
- Series II: Multi-Media, VHP2005/22.II
  - Subseries II: Still Images, VHP2005/22.II
    - Jesse Harrison and crew of 1st Fight Fighter Group of Ireland. Rineanna Airfield (now Shannon Airport), Ireland, Nov. 6, 1943; VHP2005/22.II.1
    - The "Urgin Virgin", a Douglas C-47 Skytrain which Jesse Harrison flew., 1944; VHP2005/22.II.2
    - Jesse Harrison parachuting out of his plane (right) as it is going down, Sep. 19, 1944; VHP2005/22.II.3
  - Subseries II: Moving Images, VHP2005/22.IIb
    - Oral history interview, Dec. 2, 2005; VHP2005/22.IIb.1; 1.0 dvd; Lachance, Laura May; Setelle, Benjamin (Disk DVD VHP2005/22, Box VHP Interview #1)